Guide to the Arthur F. Burns Papers, 1911-2005 and undated, bulk 1940-1987 RL.00179
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1911-1997 and undated, bulk 1940-1987, 5 boxes; 347 electronic files
  - Correspondence by Topic, 1926-1981, 9 folders
    - Academic career, 1928-1956, bulk 1928-1930 (Box 3)
      Contains correspondence related to Burns' early publications, application for a post at the University of Chicago, and the possibilities of posts at Harvard and Stanford Universities. Also included are letters of recommendation written for Burns by Wesley Clair Mitchell, Frank A. Ross, and Edwin Seligman. Correspondents include F.W. Taussig, J. van Walre de Burdes, Jacob Viner, Durand Spring, Norman Lombard, W.H. Spencer, Herbert Moore, E.S. Shaw, Frank Knight, and Theodore Schultz.
    - Columbia University, 1926-1974, bulk 1941-1948 (Box 3)
      Contains correspondence and other documents related to Burns' post at Columbia University, including appointment letters, salary information, and leaves of absence.
    - Council of Economic Advisers, 1954-1956 (Box 3)
      Contains correspondence related to Burns' post in the Eisenhower administration. Topics include legislative proposals, economic reports, employment, taxation, and the National Highway Program. Correspondents include Sinclair Weeks, Henry O. Talle, Percival F. Brundage, Moses Abramovitz, Rowland Hughes, Bryce Harlow, Maxwell Rabbs, and Douglas R. Stringfellow.
    - National Bureau of Economic Research, 1930-1962 and undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
      Contains correspondence about the appointment and work of Burns and other economists at the National Bureau of Economic Research. Also included are letters of recommendation written for Burns. Correspondents include Edwin F. Gay, Wesley C. Mitchell, William J. Carsous, Maurice W. Lee, Solomon Fabricant, Moses Abramovitz, and Simon Kuznets.
    - New York Herald Tribune, 1930 (Box 3)
      Contains correspondence regarding columns written by Burns on various economic topics. Also includes notes, drafts, and clippings of columns. One heavily-edited draft of a column on business forecasts has been removed to Oversize Box 14.
    - Private sector, 1942-1981 (Box 3)
      Contains correspondence regarding Burns' work in the private sector with companies such as Standard Oil, Salomon Brothers, Smith Barney, Calvin Bullock, IBM, Federated Department Stores, and Morgan Guaranty Trust. Correspondents include A.L. Williams, Henry Kaufman, Frank G. Zarb, and Fred Lazarus Jr.
    - Republican Party, 1955-1964 (Box 3)
      Contains correspondence between Burns and the Republican National Committee regarding contributions and strategy. Also included is correspondence and clippings about Jewish support for calendar reform. Correspondents include Charles P. Taft, Val J. Washington, and Chauncey Robbins.
    - Rutgers University, 1927-1944, bulk 1941-1944 (Box 3)
      Contains correspondence and other documents related to Burns' post at Rutgers University, including appointment letters, salary information, and leaves of absence.
  - Correspondence to Mrs. Helen Burns, 1970-1997 and undated, 13 letters
    Contains letters written to Burns' wife, Helen, both before and after his death. Letters of condolence and remembrance predominate. Correspondents include Mamie Eisenhower, Richard and Pat Nixon, Barbara Bush, Ronald Regan, and Gerald and Betty Ford.
    - Mamie Doud Eisenhower, 1970 May 25 (Box 3)
    - Pat Nixon, 1976 Jan. 8 (Box 3)
    - Richard Nixon, 1976 Aug. 13 (Box 3)
    - Hannelore Kohl (German), 1983 July 13 (Box 3)
    - Gerald Ford 1985 June 21 (Box 3)
    - Ronald Reagan, 1987 July 2 (Box 3)
      Attached: Public statement by Reagan re: Burns' death, 1987 June 26.
    - Hannelore Kohl, 1987 Dec. 16 (Box 3)
    - Telegram from Betty and Gerald Ford, 1990 Apr. 16 (Box 3)
    - Sam Nunn, 1990 Dec. 27 (Box 3)
    - Richard Nixon, 1993 Jan. 19 (Box 3)
    - Pete V. Domenici, Richard C. Halverson, Mark Hatfield, Sam Nunn, Lloyd Ogilvie, and Doug Coe, 1995 May 3 (Box 3)
    - Trent Lott, 1997 May 30 (Box 3)
    - Gerald R. Ford, May 2 (Box 3)
    - Barbara Bush, undated (Box 3)
  - Original correspondence with U.S. presidents and other notable figures
    This box contains originals of high-value correspondence without the corresponding attachments or Burns's side of exchanges. Use copies of the letters contained in this box along with their original attachments are located in boxes 1-3.
    CLOSED: Materials in this series are closed to use.
    - Moses Abramovitz, 2 items (Box 15)
    - Spiro Agnew, 3 items (Box 15)
    - George H.W. Bush, 9 items (Box 15)
    - Jimmy Carter, 12 items (Box 15)
    - Dwight David Eisenhower, 161 items (Box 15)
    - Gerald Ford, 21 items (Box 15)
    - Milton Friedman, 29 items (Box 15)
    - Lyndon Baines Johnson, 5 items (Box 15)
    - John Fitzgerald Kennedy, 3 items (Box 15)
    - Henry Kissinger, 4 items (Box 15)
    - Helmut Kohl, 7 items (Box 15)
    - Simon Kuznets, 4 items (Box 15)
    - Wesley Clair Mitchell, 8 items (Box 15)
    - Richard Milhous Nixon, 67 items (Box 15)
    - Ronald Wilson Reagan, 15 item (Box 15)
    - Helmut Schmidt, 8 items (Box 15)
    - George Stigler, 3 items (Box 15)
    - Margaret Thatcher, 3 items (Box 15)
    - Letters to Mrs. Helen Burns, 4 items (Box 15)
    - Honors and Awards: Nixon's message to the Tax Foundation's 32nd annual dinner, 1 item (Box 15)
- Honors and Awards, 1965-2000 and undated, 2 boxes
  The series contains Burns' honorary doctoral degrees, awards, and memorials from various national and international organizations.
  - Doctor of Science, Lake Forest College, 1978 June 3 (Box 4)
  - Doctor of Law, University of Vermont, 1979 May 18 (Box 4)
  - Doctor of Law, University of Vermont, 1979 May 18 (Box 4)
  - Doctor of Humane Letters, University of Dubuque, 1984 Sept. (Box 4)
  - Doctor of Law, Brandeis University, 1983 Nov. 13 (Oversize-box 14)
  - Distinguished Fellow, The American Economic Association, 1965 (Box 4)
  - The Order of Civil Merit Mugunghwa Medal, Awarded by Park Chung Hee, President of Republic of Korea, 1970 June 26 (Box 4)
  - Charles Waldo Haskin Award, New York University College of Business Administration, 1983 Nov. 14. Attached: four copies of invitation for dinner in Burns' Honor. (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Honorary Degrees and Awards (Box 4)
    - Commencement Program, Columbia University, 1970 June 2, 2 copies (Box 4)
    - Jefferson Award for Greatest Public Service Performed by an Elected or Appointed Official, American Institute for Public Service, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Arthur F. Burns' remarks at the Honors Convocation upon Conferral of the Doctor of Public Service Degree, University of Pittsburgh, 1987 Mar. 18 (Box 4)
    - Copy of Nixon's message to the Tax Foundation's 32nd annual dinner and presentation of Award for Distinguished Public Service to Dr. Arthur Burns, 1969 Dec. 2 (Box 4)
  - Convocations, commencements and other social gatherings, 1873-1987; 7 items (Box 4)
  - Medal, Republic of France, undated (Box 5)
  - Medal, Center for the Study of the Presidency, 1985 June 13 (Box 5)
  - Paperweight, Calvin Bullock Forum, undated (Box 5)
  - Sterling Silver Box, from His Admirers at the Calvin Bullock Forum (Box 5)
  - America's Democratic Legacy Award, The Anti-Defamation League, 1978 Feb. 2 (Box 5)
  - Certificate from Federal Republic of Germany, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Key to Seoul, undated (Box 5)
  - George Washington Award, The American Hungarian Foundation, 1976 Dec. 6 (Box 5)
  - Two medals awarded to Burns by the Prime Minister of Japan, 1978 Apr. 20 (Box 5)
    Images from the award ceremony are in the Photographs Series.
  - Key to Kansas City, Missouri, undated (Box 5)
  - Sash, undated (Box 5)
  - The Anti-Defamation League, 1978 Feb. 2 (Box 5)
  - Letter opener, Charles Waldo Haskin Award, New York University College of Business Administration, 1983 Nov. 14 (Box 5)
  - Letter opener, Tax Foundation Award for Distinguished Public Service, 1969 Dec. 2 (Box 5)
  - Invest-in-America National Council American Eagle Award, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Medal awarded to Burns by the President of Federal Germany, Helmut Schmidt, 1978 June 6 (Oversize-box 12)
- Journals Series, 1969-1974
  Contains photocopies of two notebooks handwritten by Arthur Burns between January 20, 1969 and July 25, 1974, when Burns was acting as the Chairman of the Federal Reserve during the Nixon Administration. The journals are comprised of 235 pages, are chronologically ordered in seven folders, and are accompanied by transcripts. They provide invaluable insights into the economic concerns and policies of the period as well as the personal and professional relations among Burns and the White House staff, Cabinet members, and the President. Burns describes at length his interactions with and personal opinions about prominent political figures of the time such as Richard M. Nixon, John Connally, H. Robert Haldeman, John D. Ehrlichman, John N. Mitchell, Spiro Agnew, Henry Kissinger, Daniel Patrick Moynihan, and George Shultz, among many others. The journals record Burns' changing opinions about President Nixon, including disagreements between Burns and the White House concerning issues such as monetary policy and wage and price controls, the Federal Reserve, and relations with international economic partners. Burns' writings also provide important insights into his and others' opinions regarding Watergate and the White House's response to it. Other topics include employment and presidential appointments. There are also entries that discuss the all-volunteer army, busing, community action programs, congressional testimony, energy, food stamps, the Headstart Program, housing, Job Corps, mass transit, malnutrition, model cities program, oil imports, revenue sharing, urban policy, welfare reform, and the Soviet immigration of Jews. There are often long time lapses between consecutive entries; however, Burns addresses the major developments during the time he did not write.
  The journals in this collection are photocopied from originals housed at the Ford Library. Since Burns' handwriting is difficult to read, Ford Library staff created transcripts which were then edited by Arthur F. Burns' former secretary, Gail Veenstra. Each photocopied page is accompanied by a transcript. Some words still remain illegible and are identified with brackets; any additional editing by Duke Library Staff is in pencil.
  - Photocopies of journals, accompanied by transcripts, 7 folders (Box 6)
- Personal Papers Series, 1926-2003 and undated, 3 folders
  Contains materials related to Burns' memorial service as well as personal correspondence, clippings, and other materials from his life, such as various versions of his CV, checks written to his father in the 1930s, a 1940 deposition regarding his legal name, and a two-dollar bill signed by Secretary of the Treasury William E. Simon. Also included is an audio recording of his memorial service in 1987. In original order as received.
  - Memorial and remembrances, 1987-2003 and undated (Box 6)
  - Cassette recording of Burns' memorial service and remarks by Ronald Reagan, 1987 (Box 6)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Digital file listening copy is available. For access to the recorded content, please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
  - Other personal papers, 1926-1987 and undated, 2 folders (Box 6)
- Photographs Series, 1958-1999 and undated, 3 boxes
  Comprised of 1092 black-and-white and color photographs, chiefly of Mr. and Mrs. Burns. The photographs come in various sizes and vary from snapshots to professional portraits; many are mounted in souvenir photograph albums. They show Mr. and Mrs. Burns at social and political occasions such as service ceremonies, lectures, meeting with the U.S. and foreign political figures, and other social gatherings. There are also images taken during trips to international locations.
  - Photographs, 1958-1999 and undated (Box 7-9)
  - Five photograph albums, color and black-and-white, 1978 (2), 1982, 1985 (2) (Box 9-10)
- Print Materials Series, 1929-2005 and undated, 2 boxes
  Composed of three subseries for writings, publicity, and materials related to the Arthur F. Burns Fellowship. The Writings Subseries is organized chronologically and includes lectures, public statements and addresses, reprints of articles, and bound volumes containing speeches he made as ambassador to Germany. The Publicity Subseries contains news clippings and articles, interviews, commentaries, and pieces published after his death. The Arthur F. Burns Fellowship (AFB) is an exchange program for German and U.S. media professionals; folders in this subseries are organized by topic and then chronologically.
  - Reprint Articles, Lectures, Statements and Addresses Subseries, 1929-1984; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - The Geometric Mean of Percentages. Journal of the American Statistical Association. (Sept. 1929). (Box 11)
    - Stock Market Cycle Research. Twentieth Century Fund Inc.: Boston (1930). (Box 11)
    - The Business Future of America, US News & World Report, May 6, 1955. (Box 11)
    - Some Lessons of the Recent Recession. (Typed address, Tenth Anniversary Meeting of the Joint Council on Economic Education, the Sheraton-Park Hotel, Washington, D.C, Nov. 19, 1958). (Box 11)
    - Progress Towards Economic Stability. The American Economic Review. Vol. 50, no. 1 (Mar. 1960). (Box 11)
    - The Basis for Lasting Prosperity. (Burns' speech delivered at Pepperdine College Los Angeles, CA, December 7, 1970). Vital Speeches. 37(6) pp. 162-166 (January 1, 1971). (Box 11)
    - A Selected Bibliography. (Typed list of Books, Articles and Interviews by Burns). Research Library Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System (July 1974). (Box 11)
    - Meet the Press. Interview moderated by Lawrence E. Spivak. Merkle Press Inc. Vol. 19, no. 21 (May 25, 1975). (Box 11)
    - The Future of the Free Enterprise System. (Reprint of award acceptance paper, Southwestern University, Memphis, Tennessee, Sept. 21, 1978). Oct. 1978. Memphis: P.K. Seidman Foundation. (Box 11)
    - The Dollar and the International Monetary System. (Reprint of keynote address, the David Horowitz Lecture, Van Veer Institute Jerusalem, Israel, Nov. 7, 1978). Dec. 1978. Washington, D.C.: American Enterprise Institute. (Box 11)
    - The Condition of the American Economy. The Francis Boyer Lectures on Public Policy. 1979. Washington, D.C.: American Enterprise Institute. (Box 11)
    - Inflation Must Be Stopped. (Reprint of keynote address, Chapman College, Orange, California, May 25, 1979). June 1979. Washington, D.C.: American Enterprise Institute. (Box 11)
    - The Perils of Inflation. (Reprint of statement to Committee on Banking, Housing and Urban Affairs, United States Senate, Mar. 14, 1980). Mar. 1980. Washington, D.C.: American Enterprise Institute. (Box 11)
    - How Inflation Influences Our Lives. (Reprint of keynote address, Hofstra University, Hempstead, New York, May 18, 1980). June 1980. Washington, D.C.: American Enterprise Institute. (Box 11)
    - Our Inflation in Historical Perspective. (Reprint of lecture, the Business Seminar Series of the University of Vermont, Burlington, Vermont, Oct. 14, 1980). Nov. 1980. Washington, D.C.: American Enterprise Institute. (Box 11)
    - The Threat of Inflation. In Hearings before the Committee on the Budget., pp. 20-73. U.S. (Jan. 21, 1981). Government Printing Office: Washington. (Box 11)
    - The Reagan Economic Program. (Reprint of lecture, University of North Carolina, Greensboro, North Carolina, Mar. 31, 1981). Apr. 1981. Washington, D.C.: American Enterprise Institute. (Box 11)
    - Regaining a Stable Price Level. (Reprint of keynote address, Xavier University, Cincinnati, Ohio, May 7, 1981). Aug. 1981. Washington, D.C.: American Enterprise Institute. (Box 11)
    - The American Trade Deficit in Perspective. Foreign Affairs. No. 62502. Summer 1984. (Box 11)
    - The Economic Sluggishness of Western Europe. (Reprint of the Dunlap Distinguished American Lecture, University of Dubuque, Dubuque, Iowa, Sept. 5, 1984). 1984. Dubuque: University of Dubuque. (Box 11)
    - The Anguish of Central Banking. Federal Reserve Bulletin. 73(5) pp. 687-698 (September 1987). (Box 10)
    - An expensive gamble to slow inflation, 1974 (Box 10)
      Scope and Contents
      In Business Week Number 2335. Bound copy of full issue.
    - Council of American Ambassadors directory, 1987 (Box 12)
  - Speeches Subseries, 1982-1985; 10 folders
    - Speeches as Ambassador, January 1985; 4 folders (Box 11)
    - Formal Speeches, 1981-1982 (Box 11)
    - Formal Speeches, 1982-1985 (Box 11)
    - Formal Speeches, 1982-1984 (Box 11)
    - Formal Speeches, 1984 (Box 11)
    - Formal Speeches, 1985 (Box 12)
    - Speeches as Ambassador to Germany, 1983-1985 (Box 11, Box 12)
  - Publicity Subseries, 1974-2004
    Contains news clippings and articles related to Burns' career. Included are interviews, commentaries, and memorial articles and obituaries following his death. There are a few articles in German. In original order as received
    - Clippings, 1974-2004, 6 folders; 5 folders (Box 12)
  - Arthur F. Burns Fellowship Program Subseries, 1993-2005
    Organized by year, these materials provide general information about the program goals along with specific details about where each fellow was accommodated the previous year, and their reports and articles published in the course of their fellowship terms. Three issues of the Arthur F. Burns International Program newsletters are also included.
    - News clippings, 1993-1999 (Box 12)
    - Arthur F. Burns Fellowship Program Newsletter, 1994-2005 (Box 12)
    - News clippings about AFB Fellowship, 1998 (Box 12)
    - Annual Fellowship Program spiral-bound notebooks, 1993-1998 (no 1999), 1-9 of 11 notebooks (Box 17, Box 12)
    - Annual Fellowship Program Notebooks, 2000-2001, 10-11 of 11 notebooks (Box 17)
- Research and Teaching Series, 1927-1930 and undated, 3 folders
  Contains undated syllabi and exam questions from economics courses taught by Burns and materials related to Burns' research on certification and labelling standards in the late 1920s. These materials include notes, correspondence responding to Burns' requests for materials, Department of Commerce publications, news clippings, book reviews, and academic articles. In original order as received.
  - Exams and syllabi, undated (Box 17)
  - Research, 1927-1930, 2 folders (Box 17)
- Oversize Materials, 3 boxes
  - Medal awarded to Burns by the President of Federal Germany, Helmut Schmidt, 1978 June 6 (Box 16)
  - Photo album, 1978 (Box 16)
  - Presidential Communications, 1953-1978, [CLOSED TO USE] (Box 13)
    Use copies of the communications contained in this box are located in Box 1 for researcher use.
    - Executive Order signed by Eisenhower, 1953 Aug. 8 (Box 13)
    - Executive Order signed by Carter, 1978 Feb. 2 (Box 13)
    - Framed Executive Order signed by Nixon with attached gift pen, 1970 Jan. 31 (Box 13)
  - Telegram from Nixon, 1969 Nov. 15 (Box 14)
  - New York Herald Tribune article draft, 1930 (Box 14)
  - Oversized photographs, 7 prints (Box 14)
  - Clippings, 2 items (Box 14)
  - Certificate from Federal Republic of Germany, 1978 June 6 (Box 14)
  - Doctor of Law, Brandeis University, 1983 Nov. 13 (Box 14)
  - Diplomas from Univ. of Pittsburgh (1987), Univ. of Maryland (1984), and the Legion of Honor, France (1976) (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Black-and-white 3/4 sepia-toned photographic portrait of Arthur Burns with pipe, circa 1940s (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Black-and-white panoramic photo of testimonial dinner in honor of Simon Kuznets on the occasion of his 60th birthday, Burns seated at long table on right, Hotel Biltmore, April 28, 1961 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Black-and-white photograph of approx. 40 individuals (White House Cabinet and advisors?) seated at table, with Nixon on right, and Burns in immediate foreground on left, 1969 Apr. 14 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Black-and-white photograph of Burns with Nixon in White House room with unidentified man in foreground, all seated, 1970 Dec. 15 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Black-and-white photograph of Burns with Nixon, wife Helen, and a Chief Justice (?) at ceremony related to Burns' appointment to Chair of the Federal Reserve Board, 1970 Jan. 30 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - "Washington Pays Tribute to Arthur Burns, 1904-1987," 1987 (large photocopy of clipping) (Oversize-folder 1)
- Digital Materials, 1920-1981 and undated
  Electronic records in this series have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use these records.
  - Correspondence Surrogates, Resume, and Eulogy, 1920-1981, undated; 352 image files and 2 disk images derived from optical disk; approximately 2.6 megabytes.
    The file includes contains some of correspondence and memoranda between Arthur Burns and presidents, vice-presidents, politicians, and prominent economists, and the letters were imaged with a digital camera.
    The file also contains Arthur Burns resume and Wesley Mitchell eulogy.